<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Examples howe mortall synne maketh the synners inobedyentes to haue many paynes and doloures within the fyre of hell And fyrst example of a father of an housholde the whiche sawe two pondes and the tourmentes of hell.</title>
            <title>Fleur des commandements de Dieu. English. Selections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849868</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849868</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 789:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Examples howe mortall synne maketh the synners inobedyentes to haue many paynes and doloures within the fyre of hell And fyrst example of a father of an housholde the whiche sawe two pondes and the tourmentes of hell.</title>
                  <title>Fleur des commandements de Dieu. English. Selections.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer: dwellynge at the sygne of seynt Ioh[a]n Euangelyste in seynt Martyns Parysshe, besyde Charynge Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1555?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Consists of selections from leaves 230-241 of "Ihesus. The floure of the commaundementes of god" (STC 23876) which is a translation of: La fleur des commandements de Dieu--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten commandments --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15040:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15040:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: Examples howe mortall ſynne maketh the ſynners inobedyentes to haue many paynes and doloures within the fyre of Hell.</p>
            <p>And fyrſt Example of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of an houſholde the whiche ſawe two pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and the tourmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Hell.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exemplar">
            <pb facs="tcp:15040:2"/>
            <head>The Examplayre vpon the paynes of Hell.</head>
            <p>MEN fynde by wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge this that whiche folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcyple reciteth in the Boke of his promptuarye &amp; ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father of a houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde yelded his ſoule to god / &amp; al his houſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de watched hym and kept his body by nyght by the dyuyne mercy he reuyued &amp; yode vnto the churche to yelde thankes vnto god. And all that he had he gaue to the churche and to the poores. Afterwarde he yode vnto an her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytage and by a water made his dwellynge and entred within the ſayde water and lette his clothes to be yſye and froſen nere to his fleſſhe. And after that he entred into a bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ryght hote and ſuſteyned ſuche payne tyll vnto the deth. And whan he was repreued to endure ſuche payne he ſayde. Yf ye had ſeene that that I haue ſeene ye ſholde do with me that I doo / or more greater thynge. And he recounted terryble thynges of the paynes of hell in ſayenge that whan his ſoule departed fro his body an Aungell led hym into a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley
<pb facs="tcp:15040:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> of infinyte greatnes. In the whiche there were two pondes / the one was ful of worme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and of flambes of fyre eygrelye brynnynge and hote. And the other ponde was froſen / &amp; there was terrible coldnes of ſnow &amp; of halfe And theſe two pondes were ful of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oules terryble tourmented / the whiche whan they myghte nomore ſuſtayne the greate cruelte of the fyre they paſſed in to the colde. And they that myght not ſuſtayne the coldenes paſſed in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hote. &amp;c. Afterwarde the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel fed hym by darkenes ryght thycke and there ſawe lytell flambe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and lytell hepes and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblementes of fyre the which proceded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the furneys of hell &amp; mounted as hye as ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles of fyre &amp; men of fyre thorowe them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded / &amp; there felte ſtynke intollerable / and there harde wepynges / waylynges / and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges in comporables and ſawe the deuyls ryght terrybles that helde hookes of fyre the whiche coueyted to catche thee Father of the houſholde to caſt hym in the furneys / but the Aungell defende that they ſhulde not touche hym. For the Iudge had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that he ſhulde returne in to his body for to do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. And there he dyd ſuche penaunce that it
<pb facs="tcp:15040:3"/> paſſed mannes reaſon. After he dyed ioyouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. &amp;c. To the purpoſe of this example that ſpeketh of the fyry ponde ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth. Qui non eſt inuentus in libro vite ſcriptus miſſus eſt in flagnum ignis ardentis &amp; ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phuris He the whiche is not founde wryten in the Boke of lyfe whan he is deed is ſent in to a ponde of fyre brynnynge &amp; of ſulpre. This po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e here wherof ſpeketh ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not of colde water or boylynge wherin the ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſonged / drowned / or boyled as falſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney makers / but it is by ſymylytude as a po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or a cawdron of fyre &amp; of ſulphre molton brynnynge and boylynge wherin the damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned be ſent there to be plonged ſmored / brent and boyled the which is the ſeconde deth that commeth after the deth corporall wherof ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſaynt Gregory in his moralles. Fit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeris mors ſine morte / finis ſine fine / defectus ſine defectu. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶Example of a Father and his Sonne the whiche were ſeene in hell in tourment of fyre brynnynge boylynge as doth the peaſon in a pot on the fyre. Quere .lxxiii. Alſo ſaynte Iohan ſayeth in the appocalyps that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mycides / fornycatours / enuenymours / ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latres
<pb facs="tcp:15040:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
/ and all ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs ſhall be ſent in to a pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de brynnynge of fyre and ſulphre the whiche is the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e deth. Vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. appoca. xxi. Pars illo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum erit in ſtagno ardenti igne &amp; ſulphure quod eſt mors ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cunda. Vnto the purpoſe of the ſecon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ponde the whiche was froſen and that the dampned paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ponde of the fire in to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the cold. It is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iob. xxiiii Ad calorem nimium tranſiet ab aquis niuiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And from the great cruelte of colde and of tormentes that the dampned haue god ſaieth in the goſpelles that they ſhall wepe &amp; gryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de theyr teeth of greate payne that they ſhall endure. Vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Math. viii.xxiiii. Ibi erit fletus et ſtridor dentium.</p>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe a ryche man was put in a Chayre of ☞Fyre.☜</head>
               <p>THE diſciple recyteth howe a deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te man ſawe by vicyon a ryche man lede in to hell that had be moche ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in this worlde and exceded in worldly glory / in glotony / lecherye / in ſonges / and in dyue reſolaces. And the prynce of the deuyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:15040:4"/> roſe vp from his chayre / came before hym and made hym to ſytte in a chayre all of fyre and ſayde vnto hym Syt thou here for the honour that thou haſt had i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worlde. And was conſtrayned to drynke of lycoure ryght bytter / ſtynkynge and foule. And they ſaide to hym that it was for that he had dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken in the world the drynk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s full of ſweteneſſes and two deuylles were there with trompettes the which blewe in his eares that the ſlambes of fyre yode out by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes / noſethrylles / mouth and eares. And it was ſayde vnto hym that it was for the bayne and ſonges that he had harde in the worlde And they put ſerpentes about his necke and vnto his armes / &amp; ſayde vnto hym that it was for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> embraceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had had in liuinge lecherouſly. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example of a woman that ſawe the paynes of her huſbande and of other dampned.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſcyple recyteth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thie the whiche foloweth the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is alſo wryten in other Bokes and ſayeth that a Knyght ryghte
<pb facs="tcp:15040:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> puyſſaunt was abandoned in torneymentes the whiche lyued miſerably / and myſcheuouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dyed. His wyfe the whiche abode wydowe was ryght deuoute and holy. The whiche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted vnto her brother Albert mayſter of the ordre of the prechours that after the deth of her ſayde huſbande ſhe was rauyſſhed in ſpyryte and ſawe by the ſoule of her ſaid huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bande great multitude of deuylles aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled. And the one of them the which appered to be mayſter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vnto his companyons and felawes that they ſhulde put a payre of hoſen on his fete of the whiche the pryckes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe called dartes perced hym from the plante of the fete tyll vnto the brayne. After<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde he made hym to be clothed in a hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergyon wherof the prickynges perced al his bodye on all partes before and behynde. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde he made to putte on his heed a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the whiche the pryckes in diſcendynge perced hym tyll vnto the plante of the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Afterwarde he made to put vpon his ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der a ſhelde otherwyſe called a marke or toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whiche was ſo heuy that all his membres were fruſſhed. After that the Prynce of the deuyle had made al theſe thinges to be done
<pb facs="tcp:15040:5"/> to the ſayde curſed ſoule he ſayde agayne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſaide deuylles. The cuſtom of this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was that after his tornementes that he vſed baynes / &amp; after his baines that he was layde in his bed and by hym a tendre mayden the whiche he enbraced and with her medled / ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propre hym ſemblable thynges. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taryenge the ſayde ſoule was moche tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented bayned in a bayne of fyre / and after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde layde in a bed of fyre brynnynge and faſt by hym a tode of the greatnes of the bed the whiche was ſo horryble &amp; had ſo terryble eyen that of the enbracynge and of the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge &amp; of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſſynge that the ſayde tode made and of the horryble lokes he was more brente and tourmented than he ne had be be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore of the ſayde armoures / of the bayne / and of the bed. Alas what paynes haue thoſe the whiche in ſuche wyſe ben tormented. That blyſſed won an that ſawe by the dyſpenſacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God the thynges beforeſayde vnto the Soule of her ſayde Huſbande was ſo moche tourmented that meruayle it was all thee dayes of her fyfe of the recordacyon of the vyſyon before reherſed of her Huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <pb facs="tcp:15040:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶Another Example howe a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uaunt ſawe his mayſter the whiche was ledde in to paynes.</head>
               <p>MEn fynde by wrytyng this the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che foloweth howe the dyſcyple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyteth in his promptuary and ſaith that there was a noble man oppreſſour and perſecutoure of poore people and loued thee worlde. The which as he reſted hym i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bed his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the which lay before his chambre was rauyſſhed by vycion before thee thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of god. And there ſawe his ſayde mayſter that was accuſed of all the thynges that hee had done / and for them ſentence of dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon was gyuen and was ledde of deuylle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before Lucyfer with great daunſynge. Vnto whom Lucyfer ſayd Approche vnto me my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne owne faythfull ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te that I may kyſſe hym. And whan he was before hym Lucyfer ſayde peas be not with the in eternyte. Agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Lucyfer ſayde. He hadde of cuſtome to bathe hym / l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>be hym to the vayne. Than was he bayned of a bayne infernall and mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che tormented with the nailes of the deuyls / 
<pb facs="tcp:15040:6"/> and ſome leeſt fyre vpon hym. After he was layde in a bedde infernall. And Lucyfer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that after the vaine men ſhulde giue hym to drynke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chalyce of the yre of god. And he was conſtrayned to drynke of fyre &amp; ſulphre molton to gyders. And as he cryed it ſuffyſed Lucyfer ſayde. He had of cuſtom to here ſymphonyes. So there aroſe vp. ii. ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonyatours the whiche were two deuylles with Inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes full of fyre the which blew agaynſte hym in ſuche maner that from his eyen and his mouth &amp; fro his noſe the flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes of fyre yode oute. After Lucyfer made hym to be brought and ſayde to hym. Thou haſt ſonge of ſonges ſinge me one &amp; he ſaide. What ſhall I ſynge / but that curſed bee the day that I was borne. And Lucyfer ſayde vnto hym Syng a better ſonge. And he an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered. What ſhal I ſynge / but curſed be the father that begate me. And Lucyfer ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym / ſynge yet a better. And the accurſed ſayde / but that curſed be that god the whiche hath ſuffred that I was borne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth vnto this purpoſe ſayeth the pſalmyſt. Non mortui landabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t te dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e: ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s qui deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt in infernum. And Lucyfer ſayde / here
<pb facs="tcp:15040:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the ſonge that I wolde haue / lede hym vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the place that he hathe deſerued. And he was caſte in to a pytte of fyre. Than the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylles made ſo great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſynge that it ſemed that all ſhulde fall. And at the ſayde dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the ſeruaunt of the ſayd man awoke. The whiche ranne vnto the chambre of his ſayde mayſter and founde hym deed. Than he tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the ſayde vyſyon. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example of a ſcoler of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys the whiche appered vnto his mayſter after his death in great tormentes.</head>
               <p>IT is wryten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> legende of the deed that one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſters of Parys na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Scilo prayed ryght greatly his ſcoter that yf he dyed that he wolde appere vnto hym after his death for to denounce vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym of his eſtate yf it pleaſed vnto God. And one tyme after he appered / the whiche was clothed with a cloke of parchemente all wryten without forth of ſophyms / and within enflombed with fyre / and the ſayde mayſter demaunded hym what he was. He anſwered
<pb facs="tcp:15040:7"/> I am he the whiche hath promyſed to come agayne vnto the &amp; he was axed of his eſtate he ſaide. This cloke weyeth more on me than a great towre / the whiche is gyuen me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re for the vaynglorye that I toke in the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes / of ſophyſtrye / that is to ſaye ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyons. And the ſlambe of fyre the whiche brynneth me is gyuen for the furtes delycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſſes that I wore. And as the ſaide mayſter ſayde that ſuche payne was lyghte to bere. The deade bodye ſayde vnto hym that he ſhulde ſtretche oute his hande and that he ſhulde f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le the lightnes of his payne. And whan he hadde ſtretched oute his hande the ſayde deade bodye lette fall a droppe of his ſwete the whiche perced the ſayde hande mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſooner than ſhulde do an arowe / and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto hym. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all ſuche. And the ſayde mayſter felte ſo horryble tourmente that he was ſo ferde that hee f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fte the worlde and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred in to relygyon. In lyke wyſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>telleth the chaunter of parye. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example of the Soule dampned that wept the tyme that he had loſte.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15040:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in the booke of dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that as a holy man was in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raiſon he herd by the wyl of god a voyce horryble wepyng. He de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded who it was that in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wyſe wepte. Anſwere was made the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſayde. I am a ſoule dampned. And he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded wherfore wepeſt thou ſo bytterly. He anſwered and ſayde that one of the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wherfore he and all the dampned ſorowe mooſt for is that that they haue lofte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumed the tyme of grace vnprofytablye in ſynnynge / wherein an houre by repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they myght haue gotten grace &amp; eſcaped the tormentes wherin they be and ſhallbe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. By this example theſe ſynners ſhulde vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the moſt great good dede that may be in them as to be in the eſtate of grace well confeſſed / &amp; repentaunce of theyr ſynnes. Alſo by that that this ſoule wept in hell is vnto the purpoſe of that that the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gylles ſaye that the dampned wepe in Hell. Vnde. Mathei. viii. Et luce. xiiii. Ibi erit fle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus et ſtridor dentium. Vnto this purpoſe tongdalus the whiche ſawe the tormentes of hell &amp; afterwarde was brought agayne tolde
<pb facs="tcp:15040:8"/> that he ſawe in hell a torment of an yzye pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de where the ſoules the whiche therin were tormented cryed ſo horryble that they were herde vnto heuen. And after where the ſayd tongdalus ſpake of the pytte of hell he herde great cryes &amp; howlynges of ſoules and thon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre ſo horryble that no man ne myghte thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke no tongue declare the horryble crye and the noyſe thee whiche was in thee ſayde tormente. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example of two men the whiche were in paynes whan S. Taurayn areyſed them.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in the legende of ſaynt Taurayn that tydyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges weare browghte vnto a ryght honorable man that his Sone and his Squyer were deed. And for to abredge the matter ſaynte Taurayne areyſed the ſayde ſone. The which yode incontynent on knees before ſaynte Taurayne and requyred hym to be baptyzed. And after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was baptyzed
<pb facs="tcp:15040:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſayde vnto his Father. Halas Father thou knoweſt what myſerable lyfe we lede &amp; what paynes thoſe ſuſteyne the whiche ben ſembla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles vnto vs. And what glorye is vnto thoſe the which loue &amp; ſerue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god the which is to be honoured of man. Certaynly I haue ſene hym to be in the company of Aungelles and to praye vnto god for vs And whan the ſayde ſone areyſed had ſpoken theſe wordes &amp; many other vnto his Father he yode on kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es before ſaynt Taurayn and cauſed hym to baptyze hym. And alſo his wyfe mother of the ſaid reyſed. And for to be ſhort in that day ſo many of great lordes as of lytell peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a thouſande &amp; two hondred perſones were baptyzed. And afterwarde at the requeſt of the ſayde ſone areyſed S. Taurayn areyſed alſo afterwarde the Squyer the whiche wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſed that he was in great paynes whan a meſſenger came to tell hym of the ſouerayne mayſter that he were brought agayne &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſaynt Taurayn. And this ſayde ſquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er areyſed ſayde vnto the ſayde ſone. He the whiche hath brought me agayne hether com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeth the that thou dyſpoſe the to retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto hym. And in contynente a Feuer
<pb facs="tcp:15040:9"/> toke hym / and after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement dyed</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example of iii. deade men arey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the whiche recompteth of the paynes of purgatorye and of hell / and howe they were in Iudgemente before God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in the Epyſtell of the holye Byſſhoppe named ſitillus that by the merytes of ſaynt Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which appered vnto ſaynt Euſebe thre deade bodyes were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyſed for to take away a great erroure the which reygned in that tyme amonge the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes that it came in the latyns of the heretikes that ſayde that the yll perſones ne ſhulde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of tormentes in hell tyll vnto the daye of Iudgement that the body &amp; the ſoule ſhuld be remyt togythers. The thre deed bodyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were areyſed lyued. xx. dayes / the which we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re demaunded why they wepte ſo ſore. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one of them ſayde vnto hym that aſked it. Yf thou knew the paines the which before yeſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daye I endured thou ſhuldeſt haue euermore cauſe to wepe. And he was requyred to tell
<pb facs="tcp:15040:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> what paynes he had endured &amp; ſuffred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell. He ſayde that the dampned and thoſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue ſo great paynes that yf a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld endure in this worlde al the paines / torm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s / and afflyctions that a man may t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e / that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhulde be but con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolacion to endure all that / in regarde of the ſeeſt payne of purgatorye / or of hell. Alſo he ſayde. Yf any lyuynge had felte the experyen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the dolour the whiche is in hell or in pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatorye / that he ſhulde loue better to endure tyll vnto the ende of the worlde wihout any remedy togythers all the paynes and tormen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes that all the men and women hath endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one after another ſyth Adam vnto now / than to be tormented one day in the leeſt pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne that is in hell or in purgatorye. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yf ye axe me what the cauſe is wherfore I wepe. It is for that that I knowledge me to haue ſynned agaynſt god / &amp; that iuſtely he punyſſeth the ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers wherfore I wepe to haue deſerued ſuche punycyon. Afterwarde he was ax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d wherin dyffereth the paynes &amp; tormentes of purgatorye / &amp; thoſe of hell. He anſwered that they ne dyffre as vnto thee qualyte and quantyte of paynes they ben of
<pb facs="tcp:15040:10"/> one ſelfe greatnes / but they dyffre in as mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes of hell haue none ende. And alſo the dampned ſhall haue augmentacion of tormentes in Iudgemente whan they ſhal there be tormented in body and ſoule. And the paynes of purgatory ſhall haue an ende. For whan the penaunce is accomplyſſhed / thoſe of purgatorye ben delyuered Alſo he was aſked yf thoſe the whiche ben in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye and in hell haue egall tormentes or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. He anſwered that the one haue more gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at tormentes and dyuers than the other after the quantyte and greatnes of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es that they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted. And alſo the dampned albeit that they ben in a place of paynes / yet feel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they more great tormentes the one than the other / after the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyte / &amp; qualites of ſin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. For in the perſone where there is more of matter of ſynne / &amp; more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely the fyre hym taketh and brynneth more cruelly. Alſo he was demaunded howe he ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the dede whan the ſoule yſſued oute from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body. He anſwered / whan myne houre of deth came in place where I was he founde ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of deuylles that a manne myghte / no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre them for the great multytude the which were
<pb facs="tcp:15040:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo horrybles to beholde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ne can thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke more great paine than it is. Any man had leuer caſte hym ſelfe more ſooner in a fyre fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bynge and brynnynge than to beholde them with the eye / the which deuyls came vnto me and brought agayne vnto my mynde all the curſed operacyons that I had done agayne god eſmouynge that I ne had more of eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the dyuyne mercy the whiche I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue greatly offended. And certes knowe ye that yf the mercy of god ne had ayded me I ne myght haue reſyſted vnto them. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſpyryte was deſtytute of all force lytell &amp; lytell I me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented vnto theyr wordes / and ſaynt Iherome arryued more clere than the ſonne with great multytude of Aungels the whiche came vnto myne ayde. And the ſayd ſaynt Iherome blamed them / &amp; they depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with great howlynges and clamours. &amp;c. For to abrydge this matter the ſaide are yſed ſayde that his ſoule was borne before god in Iudgement in lyke wiſe as a man may ſhyt the eye / but how ne of whom he ne knew. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer he ſayd al the ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es that he had done / ſpoken / and thought in all his lyfe appered clerely vnto the Iudge and before all in lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:15040:11"/> as they had ben preſent / ſo that there ne abode the mooſt lytell thought but that it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pered ſo it had be thought. Alſo he ſayd that he was replenyſſhed with ſo great feare that meruayl it was. And that great multytude of deuylles were there preſent the whiche wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe the ylles that we haue done in declaryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the place / the maner and the tyme and the ylles that men ſpoke agaynſt vs / we ne may agayne ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no maner. For the Iudge knoweth and ſeeth all. Alſo the Iuſtes and preſentes it ſene and knowe. Alas what ſhal I ſaye / we ne abyde more than the ſentence to be brought forth agayne vs. For all the preſentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ye vnto the Iudge that we ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dygne of tormentes. And almooſte no good dede appered wherin we had eſperau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the mercy of god. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ne reſyſted more as to brynge forth the ſentence the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is iuſtely gyuen agayne the ſinners that blyſſed ſaynt Iherome was preſent. Alſo we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re preſent ſaynt Iohan baptyſte / ſaynt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / and great multitude of Aungels the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che requyred of the Iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence were yet dyffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed a lytell of tyme for the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and deuocyon that we had made vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:15040:11"/> ſayde ſaynt Iherome. And for to dyſtroy the erroure the which reygned in the worlde. And he was accorded vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſaynt Iherome that that he requyred. The whiche ledde vs with hym. And ſhewed vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of the blyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed ſoules and the paynes of hell and of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorye / to thende that we myght wytnes cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne that thing that we haue ſene. The whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thynges be not here writen for bycauſe of ſhortnes. And wolde that we were put within the paynes of purgatorye to thende that we ſhulde proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> experyence of the paynes the whiche there ben in the whiche we were put. For to abrydge the ſayde ſaynt Iherome vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that we ſhulde come agayne in to our bodyes. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde wytnes that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we had ſene / &amp; vs promyſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on the .xx. day yf we dyd dygne penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld dye agayne with ſaynte Euſebe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſhulde dye on the ſayde day and we ſhuld haue glory. And ſo our ſoules were incontynent within theyr bodyes. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe a deuyll ſayde that the ſoule of the Erle Guyllaume was in horryhle payne.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15040:12"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in Dialogo Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarii this the whiche foloweth howe the diſcyple recyteth in his Boke and ſayeth that as a knyght was at the death in his bedde al alene the deuyll appered vnto hym vyſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly in forme and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blaunce of a ſheepe the which had the hornes of a gote. And when he ſe hym there in ſuche wyſe he had fere and hym demaunded what art thou and what ſekeſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou. He anſwered I am a deuyll the whiche am come for to fet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the ſoule. Vnto whom the ſayde Knyght ſayde / depart thou frome curſed thefe / I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded it vnto Iheſu Chryſt that I haue receyued in the ſacrament. And the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll ſayde. Varled yf thou wylte do me ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage I ſhall yelde vnto the helth and I ſhal enryche the aboue all thy parentes. And the knyght hym demaunded where ben thy tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours. He anſwered treaſours infynyte ben hyd nere vnto the court. And the ſaid knight aſked hym / tell me where is the ſoule of the Erle Guyllaume that whiche is lately deed. He anſwered. It is in hel in ſo great fyre that yf the moſte great mountayne were there it
<pb facs="tcp:15040:12"/> ſhulde be conſumed in leſſe of tyme than to cloſe the eye. And that payne there is but a bayne of myl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the regarde of the daye of Iudgement where he ſhal receyue the pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. And he aſked hym of another man. And he anſwered he hath be .xxxi. yeres i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paines but a Monke and Mynche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath delyuered hym by good dedes. And agayne he demaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the deuyl. From whens cameſt thou wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou came to me. He anſwered. I and my fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes were at the death of an abbeſſe away<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge her ſoule. And the knyght him demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. Howe many ben ye. He anſwered that the moſte great foreſt of the worlde hath not ſo many of leues as we were. And the knight demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him. What haue ye done. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red / Alas nothyng ſhe was a good religyous &amp; ſaint Michel came thither y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which bete vs &amp; departed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lykewyſe as departeth the poudre before the wynde / and he was axed yf he we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re at the death of ſuche an abbot. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that there is not ſo moch of grauell in the ſee as there was yf deuyls / but we ne dyd no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynge / for the vyllaynes Monkes the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che there were &amp; groned as hoggꝭ ne wold let vs to approche. And the ſayde knyght ſaide.
<pb facs="tcp:15040:13"/> Howe dare ye go vnto the deth of ſo holy a man. And the deuyll ſayde I was at the deth of the ſone of god / and ſet me on the arme of the Croſſe / wherfore dare I not than go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death of ſuche a man. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe a relygyous wolde more ſooner enter into a fyre than to beholde the Deuyll.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſciple recyteth in his pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuarye and ſayth that one ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me a relygyous came vnto the deth the whiche cryed horrybly curſed be the houre that euer I was relygyous / and after helde his peas. And within a lytell whyle afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de he began to laughe with a Ioyous face &amp; ſayde. Naye. But bleſſed be the tyme that I entred into the ordre. And blyſſed be the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous Mother of Ieſu Chryſt that I loue and agayne helde his peas. The freres y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che were by him and herde theſe wordes wept and prayed for him. Two houres after he ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de vnto a frere the which was by him / call my
<pb facs="tcp:15040:13"/> brethren. For god hath exalted theyr praiers And he ſayde vnto them whan t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. My bret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ren ye were trouble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de vnto you / but the cauſe of the worde was for that that the deuyls horryble appered vnto me / the whiche wolde rauyſſhe my ſoule. And for the drede I was rauyſſhed out of my ſelfe and curſed the houre that I entred in to relygyon I tell you that yf a great fyre were here melled with brymſtone / and that I had to choſe to put me within it or els to beholde agayne the deuylles in the forme that I haue ſene them / I ſhalbe choſe more ſooner to put me in the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde them / afterward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Quene of heuen and of mercye came the whiche chaſed away the deuylles. And whan I ſe her I concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eſperaunce / and for the greate Ioye that I hadde I haue laughed and blyſſed the houre that I entred in to relygyon and the vyrgyn Mary whan he had ſpoken theſe wordes he dyed debonayrely. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe the vyſyon of the Deuyll is horryble.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15040:14"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in ſome Bok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s this the whiche foloweth that the dyſcyple recyteth in his prompt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ary and ſaieth that the abbot of ſaynt agathe ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me vnto coleyne with one of his Monkes and a conuerſe with a woman demonyacle. And whan the abbot aſked the deuyll of ſome thynges he ne wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e anſwere. The abbot ſayde afterwarde. I coniure the by hym that I haue trayted in the Maſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou anſwere me. And incontynent the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll anſwered vnto thoſe thynges that men demaunded hym. After the abbot coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him that he ſhuld go forth of the woman. The deuyll anſwered. And whether ſhall I go. The abbot ſayde / I haue opened my mouth to thende that thou there entre. The deuyll ſayde I ne maye there entre / for this daye the ryght hault god there entred. Than the abbot ſayde. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epe vpon my two fyngers my thombe and the nexte it. The deuyll an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered I wyll not for thou haſte this daye traycted the ryght hault with them. And he ſayde vnto hym that he ſhulde go forth. The deuyll ſayde the ryght haulte ne wyll it not / 
<pb facs="tcp:15040:14"/> I ſhallbe yet two yeres in her / and than ſhe ſhal be delyuered. And ſo was it done. Than the Monke &amp; the conuerſe prayed the abbot that he wolde ſhewe hym ſelfe vnto them in forme naturall. And he fyrſt refuſed it aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde he wolde it and ſayde vnto the deuyll. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the in the vertue of Ieſu Chryſt that thou appere vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in thy natural kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. And the deuyll ſayde. And wyll ye not departe yf ye ſe me not / and the abbot ſayde naye. Than the deuyll ſhewed hym ſelfe ſo horryble within the body of the woman that it was meruayll to ſe / his eyes ſparkeled as a furnayſe embraſed in fyre ſmokynge. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd Monke and conuerſe ſawe that they fell vnto the yearth as deade for feare / the abbot hadde alſo fallen yf he had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the deuyll to take his fyrſte forme. The whiche thynges he dyd and the deuyll ſayde. Thou neuer commaunded me ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe a thyng / knowe thou for certayne that yf thou haddeſt not receyued this daye the dyuyne thynges / none of you ne hadde repor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto any man that that I haue ſhewed / weneſt thou that a man maye ſe me and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue / naye. In the ende the Monke and the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe
<pb facs="tcp:15040:15"/> were reuyued by colde water. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydred yf after a hondreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeres the dampned ſhulde be delyuered from hell.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſciple reciteth in his pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuarye &amp; ſayeth that as a man moche ſeculer and delycatyue thoughte one tyme vnto hym ſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e yf after a ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de yeres the ſoules of the damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ſhulde be delyuered from paynes. And his thoughte anſwered hym that naye. And after a hondred thouſande y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res naye. And yf after as many of yeres as there are of drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes of water in the ſee / nay. And in thynkyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſuch t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynges he was moch troubled. And as he was f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reful he began to vnderſtande &amp; to apperceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the loue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and in dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enes the whiche ronne in pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes eternall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s for a lytell of tyme that they lyue in this worlde in ioyes tranſytoryes in the wyll of the fleſſhe. A man ſhulde here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande
<pb facs="tcp:15040:15"/> that whan the ſynners dye impeny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentes / obſtynate / and abyde in theyr ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them bere with them with takynge away the gyfte of the ſayde ſynnes by contrycyon and penaunce ne without aſkynge any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ne mercy of as moch as whan they lyue in this worlde and that they haue the tyme and and the place that to do. And for as moch as the ſoule is eternall and immortall the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhall be ſent in to the fyre of hell there for to abyde / and that ſhe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all haue with her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore ſynne the whiche is the matter of the fyre that it ſhal brenne. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lyke wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule ſhall euermore ſuffre payne &amp; euermore ſhall brenne with the ſayde fyre the whiche neuer ſhall haue mercy nor grace. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example that is enioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a perſone to be in a good bedde withoute departynge.</head>
               <p>IT is wryten in the promptuarye of the dyſcyple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Byſſhop of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyll ſayde vnto hym ſelfe. Whan I was a louer of the worlde / and had gyuen me vnto worldely vanytyes I began to thynke
<pb facs="tcp:15040:16"/> one time of the eternyte of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines of hell. And I ſayde in my herte. Yf thou were eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to lye the euermore in a bedde ſofte and delycatyue in ſuche maner that thou ſhuldeſt not departe for any occaſyon ſo euer it ſhuld be / with gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at payne ſhuldeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou ſuſteyne that. How mayeſt thou than lye &amp; brenne in ſuche payne eternal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> / in tollerable in hell yf it fall that thou be thyther ſent. By this occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon I lefte all and made me Monke. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe a yonge man made hym relygyous for to thynke yf his fayre membres ſhuld be the paſture and the matter of the fyre of hell.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is writen in ſome Bokes this the whiche foloweth howe the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyple recyteth in his promptua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and ſayeth that one tyme as mayſter Iordayn perſwaded a yonge man noble fayre of membres that he ſhulde entre in the ordre of preachers / he foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de hym that he was not prompte that to do. And he ſayde vnto hym in the ende of the
<pb facs="tcp:15040:16"/> word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. I praye the that thou do it inconty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n nt for the loue of god <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beholde thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; the other fayre membres / what domage ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e yf ſo fare membres ſhall be the paſture of the fyre eternall. And he dyd it. For this thynge he entred in to the ordre and ſo contempned hymſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe for the loue of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Rapina. ¶Another Example of the punycyon of a knyght the which toke away the Cowe of a woman wydowe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Mayſters hathe wryten this the whiche foloweth howe the dyſcyple recyteth in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of ſermons and ſayeth that one tyme a knyght toke awaye the Cowe of a woman wydowe / and as ſhe wept and prayed hym to reſtore it for to nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſhe her chyldren. The knyghte anſwered. Yf I toke her not another after me ſhulde co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the whiche ſhulde take her. After her deth by the ſuffraunce of god the ſayde knyghte was ſene that fyrſt many great deuyls hede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:15040:17"/> and blacke him tormented ryght cruelly and horrybly / and ſpecyally one amongeſt all the other ceaſed not to beate hym and to tormente hym without beynge wery / or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute leuynge hym. Than the ſayde knyghte hym demaunded wherfore tormenteſt thou the more than all the other deuylles the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ben here. He anſwered / yf I tormented y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not another ſhulde the tormente as thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt to the good woman of h r Cowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou tokeſt awaye / yf thou tokeſt her not another ſhulde take her. &amp;c By this Example it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to vnderſtande that the ſayd knyght w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ryght dygne of payne and punycyon. For he dyd vnto the good woman that that he ne wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a man ſhulde do h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m agayne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of god the whiche is loue thy neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure as thy ſelfe / ne do vnto another no mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re than thou woldeſt a man ſhulde do the. Vnde Leuetici. xix. &amp; Ma. xxii. Eiliges pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ximum tuum ſecut teipſum. Et Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. iiii. Quod ab alio tibi odie fieri / vide ne tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liqn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alteri facias. Et yſido. Quod no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facis quod no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vis tibi fieri alteri nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ꝙ i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ras. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teras alu mala ne patiaris ſimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. The ſaide knyght had no wyll that a man ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:15040:17"/> take away his cowe as he dyd vnto the ſayde wydowe. And for that was he punyſſhed. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example of a rauyſſher in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the whiche toke the gote of a woman wydowe / and dyd of great oppreſſyons vnto his ſubiectes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He dyſcyple recyteth in his promp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuarye and ſayeth that a relygy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the ordre of cyſternen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boured vnto the deth / he ſawe. S. Benet the whiche came vnto the ſeperacyon of his ſoule / the which ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym many houſes of the ſaued and of the tormentes of the dampned. And amonges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other he ſawe a great prynce borne brynnyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and reſydent in a chayre of fyre. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym there was of fayre women the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che put theyr faces of fyre in his mouth / and he brynned tyll vnto the nombryll / and he was bette horrybly. This ſayde man had be a puyſſaunt prynces lecherous. After y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd lecherous he ſawe another that the deuylles dyd fle / And afterwarde they caſt and ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cled
<pb facs="tcp:15040:18"/> of ſalte vpon hym. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a gyrdyron of fyre brent him and roſted. This ſayd man had be a lorde cruell the which made of great oppreſſyons vnto his ſubiectes / and made of demaundes iniuſte vnto the poores. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the ſayde relygyous ſawe another the whiche rode a horſe of fyre and had a token of fyre the which otherwyſe men call a bokelet / and bare a gote of fyre. And after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taile of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gote he bare an habyte of amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte. This ſayd man was a rauyſſher the whiche toke the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of a woman wydowe. And whan he was ſycke he receyued the habyte of a monke / not by charyte ne by wyll to abyde in the ordre yf he myght be hole. But by the admonycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his frendes / &amp; for that he drewe the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byte of a monke after hym. Afterwarde the ſayde relygyous ſawe many other people the which ſuſteyned many other paynes after the ſymylytude of the maners that they had ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in this worlde. It is that wherof the ſage ſpeke. Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xi. Perq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccat homo: ꝑ hec &amp; torquentur. By the thynge that a man ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by that ſhall he be tormented to thende that he haue euermore remours in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence that yll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he endureth is gyuen vnto
<pb facs="tcp:15040:18"/> hym for his proper ſynnes. Vnde Yſaye vlti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo: it Marci. ix. Vermis eorum. ſ. morſus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienti non moritur &amp; ignis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> extinguitur.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example howe a Myller was borne to ſe the tormentes of hell and after was brought agayne in to his bodye.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>En fynde by wrytynge this the whiche foloweth howe the diſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple recyteth in his promptuary and ſayeth that as a man prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of the croſſe a carle vſeret bought agayne a vowe for money that he had made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulcre of Iheruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And yode vnto the dyſpenſatour fraudelently / and gaue vnto hym for his ſayde vowe an hondred ſhyllynges as he myght well gyue xlviii. li. without dyſherytynge his chyldren And as this ſayde carle ſat at the tauerne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he ſayde vnto the other the whiche had made of vowes. Ye fooles ſhal paſſe the ſee in peryll of your lyues and ſhall dyſpende your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce / I haue boughte my vowe for fyue pounde / ſaued my lyfe and dwell ſure in my
<pb facs="tcp:15040:19"/> houſe. And alſo I ſhall haue ſemblable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde as you. And in a nyght as he was in his bedde with his wyfe he herde in his mylle mouynge tempeſte In lykewyſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wheles gryndynge. And he ſayde vnto his ſone go ſe who is in the mylle. He yode and retourned anone with great feare. Of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mayſter demaunded. what haſt thou ſene. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I had ſo great feare at thee doore of the mylle / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I muſte nedely come agayne. And he ſayde yf the deuyll were there yet ſhulde I go to ſe what it is. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he caſt his veſtyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon his ſholders and yode vnto the mylle / he was all naked but of the ſayde veſtyment He opened the dore &amp; loked within / and ſawe two horſes ryghte blacke / and a blacke man by them and ſaide vnto the carle hoſt the lepe vpon this horſe the whiche is broughte vnto the. That carle had fere ond the blackeman ſayde vnto hym / what taryeſt thou / caſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the veſtyment and come / there was on the veſtyment a croſſe. He was dyſpeyred al the voyce and callynge of the deuyll keſt al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waye his veſtyment and lepte vpon the horſe And the blacke man lepte vpon the other hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / and they were led incontynente in dyuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15040:19"/> places of paynes. In the which the accurſed ſawe his father and his mother. And many other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And he ſawe a knyght named Helye of the caſtell Horſt the whiche was mounted vpon a cowes backe towardes the hornes The whiche Cowe ranne on the one ſyde and on the other and tormented hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rybly the ſayde knyght in ſtrykynge hym with her hornes on the backe. And the catle hym demaunded wherfore he ſuſteyned ſuche payne / and he anſwered. I haue rauyſſhed this Cowe and taken away from a woman wydowe without mercy. And therfore ſhe me tormenteth without mercy. Afterwarde there was ſhewed vnto the ſayde carle a ſege of fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and it was ſayde vnto hym. Thou ſhalte returne euen nowe in to thy houſe. And after thre dayes thou ſhalt come agayne in to this place here / and thou ſhalte take thy rewarde in this ſyege. After theſe wordes here the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll broughte hym agayne in to his myllt. And he founde his wife and his houſholde as halfe deed / vnto whom he tolde that / that he had ſene. And howe it hapened. The Preeſt was called for to chere hym and to counſayll hym to confeſſe hym / and to haue contrycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:15040:20"/> And he anſwered wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> profyte me theſe wordes here I ne maye repente me. For I ſe that in vayne I ſhulde confeſſe me. And I knowe that of neceſſyte it is to accomplyſſhe in me that the whiche is dyſpoſed and the ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curſed dyed ſo without receyuynge the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the churche. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Example that a knyght dyed / and after wos brought agayne into his body / the whiche recompted of a brydge ryght ſtrayte vpon a water by the whiche hym behoueth to paſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in the Dyalogue of ſaynt Gregory that a knight dyed &amp; within a lytel after came agayne into his body the which tolde that he had ſene a brydge vnder the whiche brydge ranne a water ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge and darke. And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde of the brydge there was medowes ſmellynge ſwete and adourned with all floures. And in thoſe medowes were aſſembled of people clothed in
<pb facs="tcp:15040:20"/> whyte the whiche were fulfylled of ſwetenes and odours of the ſayde floures. And at the ſayde brydge there was ſuch probacyon that whan any of the vniuſte there paſſed he fel in to the blacke water ſtynkynge / and the iuſte paſſed tyll vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place delectable. And the ſayde knyght ſawe there without the brydge a man named peter bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with great weight of yron. And he demaunded wherfore he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred ſuche payne. Anſwere was gyuen that whan men gaue hym anye for to do venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce he deſyred it more to do by cruelte than by obedyence. Alſo the ſayde knyght ſayde that he ſawe a pylgrym the which paſſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the brydge all ouer of alſo great auctoryte as he had lyued in the worlde clenely. And he ſawe another named ſteuen the whiche as he paſſed the ſayde brydge his fote ſtode in ſuch wyſe that he than fell of the ſayde brydge in lyke as halfe. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryght blacke lyfte them vp from the ſayde water the which drewe hym downewarde by the thyes. And ſome men ryght fayre clothed in whyte toke hym by the armes and they drewe hym vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / &amp; as this ſtryfe was the ſayde knyght was put agayne in to his bodye. And he ne
<pb facs="tcp:15040:21"/> knewe which of them ſhulde vanquyſſhe / but ſaynte Gregorye ſayeth that it is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ylles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had done ſtroue agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the almeſdedes. And by the other the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che drewe hym downewarde appered that he had not parfytely reſyſted vnto the ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of the fleſſhe. This Example ought to drawe all perſones to lyue clenely / purely / &amp; holyly to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide brydge vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place delectable without fallynge in to the torment beforeſaide. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynners ſhuld alſo correct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of yll &amp; to do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / or they ſhall fall of the ſayde brydge in to the ſayde water / wherin they ſhall be punyſſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>¶Another Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the vyſyon of Tong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalus the whiche ſuffred many paynes in purgatory and ſawe of the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of helle and after was brought agayne in to his body.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeres of our Lord a thouſand xlix. There was a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named To<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dalus in a Cytie of the lande of Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande. This ſayde Tongdalus was noble
<pb facs="tcp:15040:21"/> of lynage / a fayre man yong of age / curleys of all goodnes and of great honour. He was great and ryght appert of the arte of chyual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye Alſo he was well ſpekynge / and good in dyſportyng / &amp; of as moch more as he truſted in his beautye and his force of as moche the leſſe was it vnto hym of the helth of his ſoule And yf any man ſayde any thynge to hym for the helth of his ſoule he was greued with hym / he deſpyted the holy church / he ne dayg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to beholde the poores in theyr indygence / Moreouer he gaue that that was in his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes for to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſe of the worlde and many he had of frendes and of companyons And it came one daye that he ſatte at table with one of his companyons for to eat. And incontynent that he had taken of the meat he dyed of death ſodayne and the body fell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the earthe / In lyke wyſe as it neuer had had ſoule. The ſeruauntes ranne vnto hym / the meate was taken awaye / wepynges / and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacyons were made / men range the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. The people was moche ameruayled of the deth the whiche had taken this noble man ſo ſodaynely. He dyed the wedneſdaye about the houre of noone. And from that houre tyll
<pb facs="tcp:15040:22"/> vnto the ſaterdaye at noone he abode ſo the body withoute buryenge for that that in the lefts partye he had a lytell of hete. And on the ſaterdaye at noone the ſoule came agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto the body. And ſo by the ſpace of an houre he behelde thoſe the which were by him / vnto whom he made a token that he ſhuld ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the body of god. And after that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued it he began to prayſe god &amp; to yelde vnto hym graces and ſayd. Syr all puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t more great is thy mercy than all my ſynnes. And afterwarde ſayde this worde the whiche is wryten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſalter. That is to ſaye. How many trybulacyons and ylles haſt thou ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed vnto me / and I beynge conuerted thou haſt quyckened me. And haſt brought me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne from the depneſſe of the earth. And incontynent that he had ſpoken thoſe wordes he departed / and gaue vnto the poores y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that he had / and promyſed aboue all thynges to loue the lyfe that he had before ledde / and all that he had ſene and ſuffred he recompted it vnto vs and ſayde. whan my ſoule yſſued out of my body ſhe knewe and ſawe the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that ſhe had done. And ſo began ſhe to doubte. But ſhe knewe not what it was that
<pb facs="tcp:15040:22"/> ſhe ſhulde do. And ſhe wolde rentre within my body / but ſhe myght not. But ſhe ne durſt go out / for ſhe dredde her ſynnes of al partes / and ſhe ne had truſte in no thynge but vnto the great mercy of god. And ſo began to we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and to tremble / and ſhe knewe not what ſhe ſhulde do / and anone after / ſhe ſawe come vnto her ſo great nombre and multytude of deuylles that all the houſe ſtretes and place of the Cytie were full the whiche enuyro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned her on all partes / the whiche deuylles ſayde. Synge we vnto this ſoule the ſonge of deth / that we vnto her ſhulde ſynge / for ſhe is the doughter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth pardurable and the vyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre extynguyble enemy of the lyght and frende of darkeneſſes. And afterwarde and agayne her they gryn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed &amp; wheted theyr teeth &amp; ſayd vnto her. Vnhappy ſoule here is the people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſte choſen with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt entre in to hell in parbura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylyte. Thou haſte ben a nouryce of ſclaundre / a louer o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dyſcorde that we loue. wherfore art thou not proude / wherfore ne knoweſt thou not thy le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherye / where is thy vanyte and vayne glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / where ben thy laughynges ryghte vnte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred / where is thy face wherin thou truſtedeſt
<pb facs="tcp:15040:23"/> ſo moche. wherfore ne ſhytteſt thou not the eye / wherfore ne tryppeſt thou with thy fote. wherfore ne thynkeſt thou the great malyce that thou were wonte to do in vanytyes and ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. And as theſe foreſayde deuylles ſayde theſe wordes I loked towarde the heauen and ſawe a ferre of a lyght dyſcended in lyke wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe as it had ben a ſterre ryght clere and ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge. In the whiche I had eſperaunce that there was ſome ayde that god ſente vnto me. And as it approched vnto me I apperceyued well that it was the Aungell of god the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che had kepte me in this worlde. And whan he approched vnto me he alſo greted me ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely and ſayde. God the ſalue Tongdalus. ¶And whan I ſawe ſo fayre a yonge man the which greted me ſo ſwetely by my proper name by great Ioye I anſwered. Alas my Lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doloures of hel hath beſet me about. And the panges of death hath occupyed me / as it is wryten. Dolores inferni ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cumdede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt me: preoccupauerunt me la quci mortis. And the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel aunſwered. Thou calleſt me nowe lorde I haue be euermore with toe / but iudge thou not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I were dygne of ſuch great honoure The ſoule anſwered. Syr I neuer
<pb facs="tcp:15040:23"/> ſe the before. And the Aungell ſayde. From the houre that thou were borne I haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more be with the in all places where thou we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. And thou ne woldeſt neuer beleue my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayll. Than the Aungell lyfte vp his handes amonges the deuyls &amp; ſhewed vnto hym one the which dyd vnto hym worſe than the other and ſayde vnto hym that is he the which cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayled the which thou beleued &amp; dyd his wyl / but be thou ſure that thou ſhalt haue the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of god / and thou ſhalt ſuffre a lytell or tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes that thou haſte deſerued. Come thou after me &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſhal ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo kepe thou it &amp; put thou it in thy memory / for thou ſhalt returne agayne within thy body. Whan the ſoule had herde this ſhe was moche ferefull &amp; ſhe approched vnto the Aungell whan the deuylles herde this worde they were madde. For they ſawe that they ne had of puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e to do yll vnto the ſoule and blaſphemed god in ſayenge that he was not ryghtfull / for he yelded not vnto euery man after his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> And of the great woodnes wherof they were full they beteche other. And they departed from thene ſory and heuy as inraged Than the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell ſayde vnto the ſayd ſoule. Come
<pb facs="tcp:15040:24"/> after me. A ſyr thou goeſt before / theſe deuyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les ſhall take me behynde and ſhall lede me in to hell. The Aungell anſwered. Haue thou no fere for we haue more great ayde tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ne haue. Sideus pro nobis quis contra nos. Yf god be for vs there is none that may noye vs. It is wryten by the prohete Dauid. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a latere tuo mille et decem millia a dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris tuis: ad te autem non appropinquabit. Veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tamen oculis tuis conſiderabis et retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videbis. That is to ſaye a thouſande ſhall fall on the lefte ſyde / and ten thouſande on thy ryght ſyde. Certaynely they ſhal not approche vnto the. Albeit thou ſhalt conſydre by thyne eyes and thou ſhalle ſe the retrybucyon of thy ſynnes. And whan he had ſayde theſe wordes they yode forth.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of the valey.</head>
                  <p>WHan they were gone longely togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by ſo geeat darkeneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had no lyghte / but that the whiche praceded of the Aungell / they came in to a valey moche horryble / the whiche was ryght depe and full of bryn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynge coles. And about
<pb facs="tcp:15040:24"/> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> there was a couerynge of yron bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge of thyckenes ſyxt fadome the whiche was more hote than that whiche brent vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth. From thens yſſued ſo great ſtenche the whiche greued more the ſoule than all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that he had before ſuffced. Aboue the ſayde coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge dyſcended many chetyues ſoules the whiche there were fryed as a man fryeth ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con in the panne. And afterwarde they were ſtrayned thorowe the couerynge as waxe &amp; fell &amp; dyſcended in to the welle of the ſayd va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ley / vpon the brynnynge coles where they we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re tormented of a newe torment / thus ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell. This payne ſuffreth thoſe the which haue kylled fathers or mothers / or other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by delyberacyon or dede. And after this torment they ſhal beled into more great / but thou ne ſhalt ſuffre this ſayde torment albeit that thou haſte well deſerued it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of the beeſt horryble.</head>
                  <p>AFter they entred in to a way moch hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryble croked &amp; harde. And whan they had longe gone in darkenes / the ſoule ſawe a ferre a beeſt moche horryble and fere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:15040:25"/> of the greatnes incredyble / more great than all the mountaynes that he had before ſene. She had the eyen as great fyres bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / and had the mouthe ſo greate that it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto hym that there myght well entre. x.M. men of armes / there yſſued out of his mouth fyre inextynguyble / &amp; ſtynke incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. Great multytude of ſoules entred by the mouthe in to the wombe of the ſayde beeſt the whiche ſoules cryed horrybly of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that they were in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde beeſt there was great multytude of deuylles the which bette &amp; tormented the ſayde ſoules and after put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the ſayde beeſt. And whan the ſoule had longe beholden the ſayde beeſt ſhe was moche ferefull and ſayde to the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel. Syr wherfore approche we vnto this torment. The Aungell anſwered. we maye not go by other waye / for none eſcapeth this torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god hath choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in his company. This beeſt that thou ſeeſt is called Acherons the whiche tourmenteth all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarycyous. Of this beeſt it is wryten. Abſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bebit fluuium et no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mirabitur / et habet fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ꝙ influat Iordanis in os eius. That is to ſay. He ſhall ſwalowe a ſtreme or water
<pb facs="tcp:15040:25"/> and it ſhall be no meruayle / and alſo haue af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unce that the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter of Iordan ronneth yet throughe her month. And whan they had ſpoken this they came before the ſayde beeſt, and the Aungell departed and lefte the ſoule amonge the deuylles. And incontynente the deuylles beſette her about and there tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her with great tourmentes as woode dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And afterwarde they fedde her with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to the wombe of theſayde beeſt. Therin ſhe ſuffred many bytynges of dogges / of beres / of lyons / of ſerpentes / &amp; of other beeſtes that ſhe had neuer ſene ne knowen before / &amp; there had of great tormentes of deuylles / brennyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of fyre / ſharpenes of ſulphre / &amp; darkenes / woundes to plundge / to crye / and great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of dyſeaſe and of trybulacyon. There was the ſayde ſoule accuſed of her ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that ſhe had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted. And for the great heauynes wherof ſhe was full ſhe ſtrake her ſeffe on the chekes tare them with the nayles of her owne handes / &amp; wende there to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned pardurably / &amp; anone ſhe founde her ſelfe out of the ſayde beeſt / but ſhe wyſt not howe ſhe came out and ſhe was layde ferre of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che feble. Afterwarde within a whyle of time
<pb facs="tcp:15040:26"/> ſhe opened her eyen and ſawe her Aungell by her. Than had ſhe great Ioye albeit that ſhe was moche tormented &amp; began to gyue pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynges vnto our lorde of his mercy. And the Aungell touched her and comforted her. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of the ouen with the flambes.</head>
                  <p>¶Afterwarde they yode another waye / and whan they were gone longely by darkenes / they ſawe an houſe moche hyghe the whiche was rounde as an ouen. In the ſayde houſe there was wel a thouſande wyndowes / from the whiche yſſued fyre / ſtronge / ſharpe / &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hote. whan the ſoule ſawe the ſayd houſe ſhe had great fere and ſayde vnto the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell. A ſyr we approche to the gates of deth. Alas caytyfe who ſhall delyuer me fro this torment. The Aungell anſwered. From the fyre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche yſſueth out by theſe wyndowes thou ſhalte be delyuered / but in to the houſe it behoueth to entre. whan they were appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched they ſawe within the ſayde houſe in the middes of the fyre great multitude of deuyls the which helde axes / knyues / hachettes / and othee Inſtrumentes of yron ſharpe for to tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente the ſoules that were there of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſoules there was great multytude. Than
<pb facs="tcp:15040:26"/> ſayde the ſoule vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aungell. Syr I pray the yf it pleaſe the that thou delyuer me fro this torment / and in all the other where thou ſhalt ſede me I graunte me to be there tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented. And the Aungell ſayde. This tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is greater than all thoſe that thou haſt ſene / but yet ſhalt thou ſe greater. Nowe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre here for the deuylles tary for the as dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges enraged. Than the ſoule began to quake and to tremble of the great fere that ſhe had and prayed the Aungell moche that he wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de make hym to paſſe the ſayde torment / but it vayled him nothyng. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyls herde that ſhe was grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto them for to torment they toke her with theyr Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and tormented her ſharpely. The mayſter of this houſe had to name Phyſternus. His houſe was full of fyre brennynge in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſoules ſtrayned theyr teeth and wayled for the great doloure that they ſuffred. And there were men and women / not all onely of people of the worlde / but alſo of relygyon. There was this ſoule tourmented the whiche ſayde that ſhe had well deſerued that that ſhe had ſuffred. But whan it pleaſed god ſhe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de her ſelfe out of the ſayde torment and ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:15040:27"/> wyſt not in what maner. Than ſhe aduyſed her Aungell by her to whom ſhe ſayde. A ſyr where is the worde that the prophete Dauid ſpeketh. Mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i plena eſt terra. That is to ſaye. The earth is full of the mercy of God. Than the Aungell anſwered and ſayde. By thoſe wordes many ſoules be deceyued. God is ryghtwyſe thoughe that he be full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy / &amp; many ſynnes he vengeth &amp; punyſſheth / and alſo he pardoneth. Yf god pardoned all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes wherfore ſhulde the men be iuſt. And yf a man ne dredde the tormentes / wherfore ſhulde he drede to do ſynne &amp; his wyll. And what ſhulde it nede that theſe ſynners ſhulde repent them and confeſſe them of theyr ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes yf they ne dredde god. God by his great mercy ſpareth the ſynners in theyr lyfe and taryeth them for that they ſhulde do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce But yf they ben obſtynate in theyr ſynnes and wyll not reuerte / he them punyſſhed for theyr ſynnes after theyr deth. And God ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time taketh away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gooddes te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poralles from the Iuſt for to punyſſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porally of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me outrages y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue done / &amp; alſo to then<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they enpryde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. But he kepeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gooddes pardurables of his glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15040:27"/>
                  <head>¶Of the cruell Beeſt and of the yſye ponde.</head>
                  <p>¶After the Aungell led the ſoule in to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place wherin they ſawe a beeſt moche meruaylous the whiche had two fete and .ii. wynges and the necke ryght longe. And his nebbe and his nayles were as yron / and from his ſayde nebbe yſſued a flambe of fyre by ryght great ſharpenes &amp; force. And the ſayde beeſt was vpon a ponde full of ſtronge yſe / the whiche beeſt deuoured the ſoules within his wombe in ſuche maner that they became as vnto nothynge by the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that they ſuffred. Afterwarde he put them out of his wombe within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yſe of the ſayde ponde. And there were they tormented of newe torment. And all the ſoules the whiche in to the ponde dyſcended were in throwes in lykewyſe as women with chylde. And not a lonely the women / but alſo the men as the women. And within theyr belyes they felte the ſharpe by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges that the ſerpentes made of the whiche they were engryped. And there were the cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyues ſoules tourmented. And whan the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me came &amp; approched that they ſhulde chylde they cryed ſo horrybly that they fylled hell of
<pb facs="tcp:15040:28"/> noyſe and of hon ſynges. Than they chylded ſerpentes as wel the men as the women. And the ſayde ſerpentes yſſued not onely by the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres wherby the women chylde naturally. But alſo by the armes / the feete / and all the other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres yſſued oute the horryble beeſtes the whiche had heade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of fyre brynnynge mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſharpe / wherwith they tormented ryghte cruelly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whens they yſſued. And the ſayde beeſtes had horryble tayles &amp; nedles and aboute theyr tailes made as they were crochettes and hookes made as yf they were crochettes. And whan they yſſued from the ſayde caytyues ſoules yf they myght not drawe theyr tayles after them for the hookes they returned theyr nebbes &amp; ſmote y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules and gnawed then vnto the ſynewes &amp; bones and of the great payne &amp; tormente that they ſuffred they keſte ſo great and horyble cryes that they were herde vnto heauen. Moreouer the ſayde ſoules were replenyſſhed of dyuers maners of beeſtes on theyr membres the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che did them eate and gnawe vnto the bones. And they had tonges y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which faſtened with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayde ſoules tyl vnto the lightes. This payne ſuſtayne the falſe Monkes / chanons / 
<pb facs="tcp:15040:28"/> the falſe Nonnes / and theſe other benefyced of holy churche the whiche haue not wel kept theyr bodyes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euyll doyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> / ne theyr mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes from euyll ſaynge and ſpekynge. Alſo thoſe the whiche hath vſed Lecherye ſuſteyne this payne and torment. And for that that thou arte cuſpable it behoueth the to ſuſteine this ſayde tormente. whan the deuylles herde this worde they toke the ſayde ſoule and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it to the ſayde beeſt to tourment and to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoure. And whan ſhe was in torment as the other ſoules and that ſhe was engryped with ſerpentes as the other / and whan the tyme ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me that ſhe ſhulde chylde the Aungell came to her and touched her / and ſhe was inconty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent hole / and ſayde vnto her / come after me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of the valey of ſmythes.</head>
                  <p>¶Afterwarde they yode in to another way moche horryble &amp; dyſeaſefull full of ſo great darkenes that they had no lyght but of the clerenes of the Aungell. And it ſemed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deſcended from a ryght hyghe mountayne in to a great and depe valey. And them ore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they yode the leſſe had the ſoule of eſperaunce for to returne vnto lyfe. Than the ſoule ſayd vnto the Aungell. Syr whyther gowe. The
<pb facs="tcp:15040:29"/> Aungell anſwered. This waye ledeth vnto death And the ſoule ſayd. what is that than that the ſcrypture ſayth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ata eſt via que du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cit ad mortem / et multi ſunt qui intrant per eam. That is to ſay that the way the whiche is large ledeth vnto death: and many there ben the whiche entre &amp; go by that way. The Aungell ſayde. Of this ſpeketh not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſed way of the worlde wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men in to this way. And whan they were deſcended into the ſayde valey moch de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe they ſawe there of forges. Than the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſayd vnto the ſoule. The mayſter of this valey is called Vulcane the which by his en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyn and falſenes hath caſten many ſoules in to paynes and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Than ſayde the ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le vnto the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell. Syr ſhall I ſuffre this tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. The Aungell anſwered / ye / thou ſhalte ſuffre this torment. And whan the deuylles her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that worde they beſet the ſoule about and to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke it with theyr Inſtrumentes of yron y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they helde / and ſayde vnto the holy Aungell none harme / and keſte it in to a chymney full of fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re brynnynge. And began to blowe the fyre of theyr furneys in lykewyſe as men blowe whan the yron is in the furneys. And ſo they torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:15040:29"/> the ſoules the whiche were there tyll that they came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>to nothynge. And whan they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re ſo brente and tourmented they toke t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſayde ſoules with theyr Inſtrumentes of yron .xx. an hondred or two hondred and layde them on a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an anuelde of yron and the deuylles the whiche were in other for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſayde. Caſt vnto vs theſe caytyues ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s we ſhall yet torment them agayne. Than the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls keſt them vnto them agayne the whiche were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other forges. And after that they had ben there ſtrongly payned and tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented they keſt them vyolently vnto thoſe of the fyrſte forges. And before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they came to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de they were taken agayne and ſo they keſt them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one vnto an other and tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented tyll vnto that / that the ſkynnes / the fleſſhe / and the bones came as vnto nothyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. Of this matter is wryten. Prouerbioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ix. Parata ſunt deriſoribus ſupplicia / et mal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lei percutientes ſtultorum corporibus. After that the caytyues ſoules were ſo torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is ſayde they deſyred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth but they might not dye. Vnto this purpoſe it is wryten. Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>calipſis. ix. In diebus illis querent homines mortem et non inuenient eam / et deſiderabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:15040:30"/> mori et more fugiet ab eis. And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſoule had ſuffred longely theſe tormentes the Aungell came vnto her and toke her and had her out of the fyre where ſhe was / &amp; ſayde vnto her. Howe feleſt thou thy ſelfe nowe. Remembre the that for as moch as thou haſt done thy wyl &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delyte of thy body thou haſt ſuffred ſo great torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. But the ſoule had not ſo moche force y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe myght anſwere one worde for the great torment that ſhe had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred. Than the Aungel ſayde vnto the ſoule. Illud pſalmi. Dominus mortificat et viuifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat deducit ad inferos et reducit. Comforte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the / for our lorde quyckeneth &amp; mortyfyeth / ledeth in to helles &amp; bryngeth agayne. And albeit that the tormentes that thou haſt ſene ben moche great yet ſhalt thou ſe moche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re greater from the whiche thou ſhalte be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered by the mercy of god. And know thou that all thoſe ſoules that thou haſt ſene here abydeth the Iudgement of God. But thoſe the whiche thou ſhalte ſe from henſforth ben all redy Iudged. Gowe nowe forwarde for thou art not yet comen vnto the paynes of hell. And the Aungell touched her and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as he had ben accuſtomed for to do. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15040:30"/>
                  <head>¶Of the pytte of Hell.</head>
                  <p>¶After that they entred in to a waye / and whan they were a lytell gone forwarde in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge one vnto the other there came to the ſoule ſodayne horrour and colde intollerable and ſtynke and darkenes more thycker than thoſe before / trybulacyon and anguyſſhe ſo great that it ſemed vnto the ſoule that all the foundementes of the earth trembled vnder her fete &amp; ſayde vnto the Aungell. Syr wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore is it that I ne may holde me on my fete as I haue accuſtomed to do. And whan ſhe had ſayde this ſhe ne myght remene from the place for the great feare that ſhe had / and incontynent the Aungell departed in ſuche maner that ſhe myght no more ſe hym / and forthwith ſhe began to dyſpayre. For ſhe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that the whiche is wryten. Eccleſiaſtes. ix. Nec opus / nec ratio / nec ſapientia / nec ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia erunt apud inferos que tu ꝑperas. That is to ſay that in hell there ne is operacion / ne reaſon / ne wyſdom / ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge wherby man may ayde hym. The caytyne ſoule was in ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kewyſe / for ſhe myght not helpe herſelfe / the whiche herde terryble cryes and howlynges of ſoules / and thondre ſo horryble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man
<pb facs="tcp:15040:31"/> may thynke it ne tonge declare the horryble crye end the noyſe that there was. Vnto this purpoſe God ſpeaketh in the Goſpell. Illud Mathe. xxii. &amp; .xxiii. Ibi erit fletus &amp; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentium. Than the ſoule loked about her for to knowe yf ſhe myght ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way wherby they were comen / and ſhe ſawe a great ſquare dyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in lykewyſe as a cyſterne. And from that dytche yſſued out a pyller of flambe and of ſmoke togythers moche horryble &amp; ſtynkyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. And the pyller of fyrs was ſo hyghe that it ſtretched vnto the heauens. And in the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be there was great multytude of ſoules and of deuylles togythers the whiche mounted with the ſayde flambe in hyghe in lyke wyſe as lytell flambes. And of tormentes the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che they ſuffred they came as vnto nothynge &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they fell agayne in to the dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>che tyl vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> botom. Vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe of this ſaieth the Pſalmyſte. Tu vero reduces me in pute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um interitus. And whan the ſoule had behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den this ſhe wolde haue drawen her a backe / but ſhe ne myght lyfte her fete fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And whan ſhe had aſſayed many tymes to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moue her and that ſhe myght not ſhe was mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ferefull / and of the great woodnes that
<pb facs="tcp:15040:31"/> ſhe had ſhe tare and rent her chekes with her owne handes and nayſes &amp; cryed. Alas cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue wherfore may not I dye. And the deuyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les the which mounted with the ſayde flambe herde the ſayd ſoule in ſuch wyſe crye ſo they beſet her about with theyr Inſtrumentes of yron wherwith they torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the ſoules and ſayde in this wyſe. Caytyue ſoule worthy of payne and torment from whens art thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hyther / thou ne haſt yet nothynge felte ne ſuffred / thou ſhalt endure nowe that that thou art worthy by the ſinnes that thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted. From the whiche torment thou ne mayeſt neuer departe ne within it dye / but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore thou ſhalt lyue and brenne in torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without lyght / comfort ne helpe. And from nowe forth thou ne mayſt haue mercy. For thou art comen vnto the gates of death / and thou ſhalt be borne ſtreyght in to the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of hell. He that hath brought the hyther hath deceyued the / nowe let hym delyuer the from our handes yf he can / for thou ſhalt ſe hym no more. And they ſayde the one vnto the other. wherfore tary we ſo longe that we ne gyue this ſoule vnto Lucyfer for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure it / and ſo they thretened it of death per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durable.
<pb facs="tcp:15040:32"/> And theſe deuylles aboueſayde we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re blacke as coles with horrible lobes &amp; theyr eyen were as the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge. And theyr teeth as whyte as the ſnowe / and they had tayles lyke as ſcorpyons / and theyr clawes of yron and great large wynges. And whan they had ſayd theſe wordes the holy Aungell appered vnto the ſayd ſoule and ſayd to her. Enioy ye doughter of lyght for thou ſhalt ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue mercy and not Iudgement. Thou ſhalt ſe of great tormentes and paynes / but thou ſhalt ſuffre none Come tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after me &amp; I ſhal ſhewe vnto the / the ryght curſed enyemye of humayne lygnage. Thoſe the whiche ben the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re haue no lyght / &amp; they ſhall not ſe the / but thou ſhalt ſe them well and theyr tormentes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of the Prynces of darkenes and of theyr curſed felowes the whiche ben in paynes.</head>
                  <p>¶After theſe thynges ſpoken and ſene the ſoule approched vnto hym &amp; ſawe the prynce of darkenes in the botom of hell / &amp; what and howe great tormentes ſhe ſawe there the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendement ne may comprehende it / and man ne may expreſſe it ne declare. That is to ſay yf he had an hondred heades / and that euery heade had an ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred tonges / yet they myght
<pb facs="tcp:15040:32"/> not recompte the paynes of hell. There was one the ryght worſt deuyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was more greater than all the beaſtes that he had ſene before. The which was blacke as Rauen, He had the forme of the body of a man from the feete vnto the heed except that he had well a thouſande handes. And he had atayle well an .C. cubytes long / and .x. of greatnes. And he had nayles of yron great &amp; longe as well on the feete as on the handes longer &amp; greter than the ſperes of knyghtes. His nebbe was moche longe and great. His tayle was ryght longe and ſharpe all full of pryckles ſharpe poynted for to greue and torment the myſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſoules. And that mooſt horryble deuyll laye vpon a gred yron of yron / vnder the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che there was great habundaunce of bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge coles. Alſo there was great multytude of deuyls the whiche blewe and kyndled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre. About the enemy there were ſo many deuyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and of curſed and myſerable ſoules that no man myght beleue that of all the worlde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnynge myght be yſſued &amp; brought forth ſo many ſoules. And the deuyll was bounde by euery Ioynture of all his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres with great chaynes of yron and of copre bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge.
<pb facs="tcp:15040:33"/> And of great torment and vehement woodnes wherof he was full he turned hym f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om the one ſyde vnto the other / and ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out his handes in the multytude of the ſayde ſoules and toke them and ſtrayned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in lykewyſe no men maye do a cluſtre of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes in theyr handes for to make the wyne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me forth. And in ſuch maner he ſtrayned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he eyther brake theyr heedes / or theyr fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / or handes / or ſome other membres. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde he ſyghed and blewe and dyſperpeled the ſayde ſoules in to many of the tormentes of the fyre of hell. And incontynent that pyt or well wherof we haue before ſpoken keſte ſtynke and horryble flambe. And whan that cruel beeſt drewe agayne vnto hym his breth all the ſayde ſoules that he had ſhed with fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and ſulphre fel and entred in his mouth / the whiche he deuoured. And whan ſome ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les eſcaped hym by aduenture betwene his handes he ſmote them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th his tayle. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll the whiche in ſuche wyſe tormented the ſoules horrybly was tormented aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Than the Aungell ſayde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule. This deuyll that thou ſeeſt here is call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfer the whiche is the fyrſt creature that god
<pb facs="tcp:15040:33"/> made the whiche was in the delyces of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe before that he deſcended from heauen / and yf he were not bounde he wolde do many euylles &amp; parturbacyons. And they the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thou ſeeſt the which be with hym there are a partye of the Aungelles of darkenes. And the other partye ben men and women the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ben deſcended from Adam the which ben all redy Iudged the whiche abyde many the which haue renyed Ieſu Chryſt / or doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racyons of them the whiche renye hym. Here be the yll Prelates and Prynces of whom it is wryten. ſapientie .vi. Potentes pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menta patientur / fortioribus autem fortior inſtat cruciatio. That is to ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe that be myghty in dygnyte and in power ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre tormentes with great puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. That is where as they haue myſche nouſlye vſed the puyſſaunce that god hath gyuen vnto them. All the other tormentes that thou haſte ſene albeit that they be ryght great yet are they nothynge to compte in regarde of this here. And the ſoule ſayde. Certesſyr thou ſayeſt true / for I am more greued and tormented to ſe alonely the torment and to fele the ſtynke the whiche is there than all the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that
<pb facs="tcp:15040:34"/> I haue ſuffred hyther to wherfore I praye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the yf it pleaſe the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou take me from hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Alſo I ſe many of my felowes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I loued mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che &amp; helde theyr company moche dere where as I haue nowe great horrour for to ſe them. And certaynly I vnderſtande &amp; knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf the great grace &amp; mercy of god w re not my ſuccoure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue deſerued for my ſynnes to be punyſſed and tormented eternally as they ben. And the Aungell ſayde vnto hym. O my blyſſed come and conuerte the in thy reſt / for god hath done well vnto the / thou ſhalte not ſuffre theſe tourmentes here. And thou ſhalt ſe them no more yf thou forget not the thynges that thou haſt ſene / and yf thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them not agayne. The ſoule of the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Tongdalus ſawe many other tourmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and of the Ioyes of the ſaued the whiche hath be lefte by cauſe of ſhortnes for they ben moche longe to recounte and wryte. ¶By the ſcryptures and Examples beforeſayde it doth appere that the ſynners in obedyentes vnto god ſhulde correcke them and amende whyles that they lyue in this worlde yf that they wyll eſcape and eſchewe the ineſtyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tourmentes of hell and gette the Realme
<pb facs="tcp:15040:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the glory eternall. Vnto the whiche glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye we maye go / cum illo qui eſt benedictus in infinita ſecula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth the Examplayre vpon the paynes of hell.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="example">
            <head>¶Ieſus. ¶Hereafter foloweth an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that the name of Ieſus doth many goodneſſes. And howe it de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered a man fro many perylles and tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wryten in many Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes that as ſeynt Patrycke preached in Irlande he praied God deuoutly that he wolde ſhewe hym ſome token by the whiche the wycked euyllmen myght haue feare and alſo repent them. And ſodaynly a ryght great hole or pytte appered and it was reueled vnto hym that the place of purgatory was there. In the whiche pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce yf any wolde deſcende he ſhulde haue none
<pb facs="tcp:15040:35"/> other payne. Many the which herde this thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge therin entred the whiche came neuer agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. And a man named Nycolas the whiche had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted many ſynnes there deſcended to thende that he myght repente hym of his ſynnes. And he founde fyrſte an oratory and whyte Monkes the whiche ſayde vnto hym. Be thou ſtedfaſt and conſtaunt. For it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the to ſuſtayne many te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacions. And he them demaunded what remedy he myght haue agaynſt the ſayde temptacions. They anſwered whan thou f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſt thy ſelfe tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with paynes crye haſtely. O Ieſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte adiuua me. That is to ſaye. O Iheſu Chryſt helpe me. And whan that he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from them the deuylles ranne ſoday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely vpon hym in lykewyſe as wylde beeſtes famyſſhed. And as they dyd in this wyſe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym he recorded hym of his counſayle and ſayde. O Ieſu Chriſte adiuua me. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contynente he ne wyſte where the beeſtes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came. He yode furthermore &amp; founde a tyght great fyre in to the whiche the deuylles keſt hym. And incontynente that he had ſayde. Ieſu Chriſte adiuua me / forthwith the fyre was put out and quenched. He walked yet
<pb facs="tcp:15040:35"/> further and ſawe a well ryght depe from the whiche yſſued ſmoke and great clamoure of ſoules the which were tourmented. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuyls had caſten hym within it he cryed. Ieſu Chriſte adiuua me. That is to ſay. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chryſte helpe me / and forthwith he was delyuered. At the laſt he ſawe a brydge that was ryght narowe and ſtrayte. And there he had great terrours / the whiche brydge hym be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>houeth to paſſe / but he myght not. And he ſette one of his fete vpon the brydge and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Ieſu Chriſte adiuua me. And ſo he ſaide at euery ſteppe tyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had paſſed the brydge on the other ſyde. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he was paſt he came vnto a fayre medowe wherin grewe many fayre and delectable floures / of the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che floures and medowe proceded good odou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res and ſmelles. And afterwarde he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto lyfe and .xxx. dayes paſſed he came vnto Paradyſe by the Inuocacion of our bleſſed ſauyoure and redemptoure Ieſu Chryſt. ¶Vnto the Example of the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde man the whiche was delyuered from al tourmentes and paynes incontynente that he had called the helpe of Ieſus. In lykewy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thou man and woman call deuoutly the
<pb facs="tcp:15040:36"/> name of the bleſſed Lambe Ieſus in all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſytyce / fortunes / tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / loſſes / temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions / ſickeneſſes / neceſſityes / anguyſſhes / perylles / infyrmytyes / and thynges doubta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles / &amp; well ſhall come vnto the. This name Ieſus is interprete ſauyour. Ieſus interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur ſaluator. For by the meryte of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon he ſaued all the worlde. He brake hell / ſaued and delyuered afthe good perſones the whiche were in the lymbe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fathers &amp; opened Paradyſe vnto all good chryſtyane. Alſo I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſus is the kynge of kynges / the Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of Iudges / and of all great and lytell. It is he that gyueth Ioye &amp; beatytude eternall vnto the good / &amp; that punyſſheth and damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the euyll / Ieſus is holy and debonayre vnto the good / &amp; alſo he is terryble and cruel vnto the euyl. And therfore ſayeth the pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſt. Sanctum &amp; terribile nomen eius initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſapientie timor domini. Alſo the name of Ieſus is in excellence aboue all other. Vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paul. ad Phyl. Docatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius ſuper omne nomen. Alſo the name of Ieſus is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; dred aboue all names / &amp; in namynge hym all creatures reſonables ſhulde bowe the knee / be it in Paradyſe in this worlde / or in
<pb facs="tcp:15040:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> hell. Vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Paul. ad Phi. In nomine Ieſu om<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e genu flectatur celeſtium / terreſtrium / et infer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norum. The men and women of this worlde cal hym in theyr beſyneſſes and neceſſytyes / and the deuylls of hell dred hym. For to be ſhorte the name of Ieſus ought to be loued / honoured / called dred / and redoupted / for it is replenyſſhed with bountye / beautye / and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes infynyte and in enarrable. That is the whiche paſſeth all entendementes. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>¶Finis</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted by me Robert Wyer: dwellynge at the Sygne of ſeynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſte in ſeynt Martyns Paryſſhe, beſyde Charynge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>¶Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15040:37"/>
            <figure>
               <head>ROBERT WYER·</head>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:15040:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
